<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>associative processing | Penn Computational Intelligence Lab</title>
    <link>https://penn-cil.github.io/tags/associative-processing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://penn-cil.github.io/tags/associative-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>associative processing</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 16:00:10 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://penn-cil.github.io/img/logo.png</url>
      <title>associative processing</title>
      <link>https://penn-cil.github.io/tags/associative-processing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Dimensional Associative Processor (2D AP)</title>
      <link>https://penn-cil.github.io/project/two-d-ap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 16:00:10 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://penn-cil.github.io/project/two-d-ap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The research project, titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Associative In-Memory Graph Processing Paradigm: Towards Tera-TEPS Graph Traversal In a Box&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, won the &lt;strong&gt;NSF CAREER Award&lt;/strong&gt; in 2018. In this research, we developed a radically new computing paradigm, namely two-dimensional associative processing (2D AP) to further advance our previous FPGA-based graph processing architectures and fundamentally address their limitations. Mathematically, 2D AP is a new general-purpose computing model that exploits an extra dimension of parallelism (both intra-word and inter-word parallelism) to accelerate computation as compared with traditional AP which only exploit inter-word parallelism. It is particularly beneficial for massive-scale graph processing. For the first time, we provide a theoretical proof that 2D AP is inherently more efficient as measured by &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;architecturally determined complexity&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; in runtime/area/energy than both von Neumann architecture and traditional AP paradigm in performing graph computation. We also provide detailed micro-architectures and circuits to best implement the proposed computing model, with domain-special language support. A preliminary published version of 2D AP [&lt;a href=&#34;khoram-2018-cal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Khoram2018CAL&lt;/a&gt;] was recognized as &lt;strong&gt;best of CAL&lt;/strong&gt; (IEEE Computer Architecture Letters) in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
